A Guide to the Records of Western State Hospital, 1825-2000
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Records of Western State Hospital, 1825-2001
The Library of Virginia
31030, 31353, 31704, 32451, 41253, 41283, 41404, 44812, 45553, 50576, 50989, 53601, 53661
115 cubic feet of records (260 boxes) and 1065 volumes.
Western State Hospital
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
As of September 11, 2019, medical records will be open 125 years after the date of creation or after date closed, whichever is later. The Health Insurance Portability and Accountability Act (HIPAA) requires that individually identifiable health information of a decedent be protected for 50 years following the date of death of the individual (45 CFR 164.502(f)).
Protected health information (PHI) as defined under the Privacy Regulations issued under the Health Insurance Portability and Accountability Act (HIPAA) includes, but is not limited to, personally identifiable information such as names, addresses, and social security numbers. Restricted material may include, but is not limited to: patient lists, patient admission registers, treatment registers and medical record files. Please contact Archives Research Services for further information.
Alternate Form Available
Admission Registers, 1828-1896, also available on microfilm for research use - Miscellaneous Reels 6295-6297. Interlibrary Loan copies of microfilm with unrestricted records also available.
Miscellaneous Reel 6295 - v. 247
Miscellaneous Reel 6296 - v. 248 and v. 249
Miscellaneous Reel 6297 - v. 250
Miscellaneous Reel 6301 - v. 266
Acquisition Information
Accession 31030 transferred by Frank Demory, Western State Hospital, 12 March 1981.
Accession 31353 transferred by Francis L. Demory, Western State Hospital, Box 2500, Staunton, Va., 11 March 1982.
Accession 31704 transferred by Francis L. Demory, Western State Hospital, 14 March 1983.
Accession 32451 transferred by Western State Hospital, Shenandoah Geriatric Treatment Center, P.O. Box 2500, Staunton, Va., 30 July 1985.
Accession 41253 transferred by Kim Burns, Western State Hospital, Administrative Office, P.O. Box 2500, Staunton, Va., 15 June 2004.
Accession 41283 transfer information unavailable, accessioned 30 June 2004.
Accession 41404 transferred by Kim Burns, Western State Hospital, Administrative Office, P.O Box. 2500, Staunton, Va., 25 August 2004.
Accession 44812 transferred by Michelle L. Porter, Health Information Management Department, Eastern State Hospital, 4601 Ironbound Road, Williamsburg, Va., 17 February 2010.
Accession 45553 transferred by Kim Burns, Western State Hospital, P.O. Box 2500, Staunton, Va., 8 June 2011.
Accession 50576 transferred by Kim Burns, Western State Hospital, P.O. Box 2500, Staunton, Va., 19 September 2012.
Accession 50989 transferred by Judy Ross, Commonwealth Center for Children and Adolescents, 1355 Richmond Road, Staunton, Va., 15 August 2013.
Accession 53601 transferred by Kim Burns, Western State Hospital, 29 April 2022.
Accession 53661 transferred by Kim Burns, Western State Hospital, 12 July 2022.
Historical Information
In January 1825 the Virginia General Assembly passed legislation providing for the construction of an asylum in the western part of the state. A Court of Directors was commissioned by the Governor to serve as the asylum's governing body and charged with purchasing a site close to the town of Staunton, west of the Blue Ridge Mountains, on which to build an asylum to house the mentally ill of western Virginia. The institution, which became known as Western Lunatic Asylum, was the second mental health facility built in the Commonwealth of Virginia. The buildings and surrounding gardens were designed to embrace the idea of "moral therapy" for mentally ill patients by providing an aesthetically pleasing and tranquil atmosphere in which patients lived comfortably, exercised and worked outdoors.
Western Lunatic Asylum opened in 1828, accepting both male and female patients suffering from a variety of mental disorders. Common diagnoses included "hard study," "religious excitement," and "debility of the nervous system." The asylum was overseen by a Keeper, a Matron and a visiting physician during its earliest years. The hospital also employed attendants, gate keepers, night watch personnel, farm hands, and a steward who handled the day-to-day financial operations. The first superintendent appointed to oversee Western Lunatic Asylum was Dr. Francis T. Stribling. Dr. Stribling was a proponent of the moral therapy approach, and was a leader in the early mental health community. Dr. Stribling was one of the thirteen founders of the Association of Medical Superintendents of American Institutions for the Insane, which later became known as the American Psychiatric Association. Dr. Stribling served as the hospital superintendent and as a physician until his death in 1874.
It should be noted that the hospital underwent a short-lived name change between 1861 and 1865, when it was known as Central Lunatic Asylum. (It should not be confused with an asylum of the same name later built in Petersburg, Virginia to house African American patients). From 1865 to 1894 the name was again Western Lunatic Asylum. However, in 1894 the General Assembly passed legislation changing the name to Western State Hospital.
Another highly influential superintendent at Western State Hospital was Dr. Joseph S. DeJarnette. Dr. DeJarnette was hired as a physician in 1889 and was appointed superintendent in 1905. His tenure was the longest of any superintendent at Western State. Dr. DeJarnette was also responsible for founding the DeJarnette State Sanatorium, which housed patients with the ability to pay for their treatment. Dr. DeJarnette remained the superintendent of Western State for 38 years, retiring in 1943 with many accolades. He served as superintendent of the sanatorium from its formation in 1932 to his full retirement in 1947. Dr. DeJarnette's involvement in the eugenics movement and his support of the involuntary sterilization of mental patients has in more recent years earned him a less favorable reputation.
Many of Western State Hospital's original structures remain standing on what is referred to as the "Old Site." Many of these structures are historically and architecturally significant and are listed on the National Register of Historic Places. During the 1960s a newer hospital facility was constructed, and over the next decade patients and programs were slowly moved to the "New Site." Deinstitutionalization efforts and increased focus on localized community programs resulted in lower patient census numbers starting in the 1970s, and by the mid-1970s the Old Site had shut down completely. The Old Site was later converted into Staunton Correctional Center, which it remained until its closure in late 2002. The original grounds of Western State Hospital were eventually sold and are being converted into condominiums and retail space as part of an urban redevelopment plan.
Western State Hospital continues to serve the mental health needs of Virginia's citizens from the New Site in Staunton, Virginia. The hospital is part of the Virginia Department of Behavioral Health and Developmental Services (DBHDS) and is governed by the State Board of Behavioral Health and Developmental Services.
Scope and Content
The Western State Hospital collection contains a wide variety of bound volumes and paper records spanning more than 170 years (1825-1998). Included are administrative records such as annual reports, correspondence, office and subject files, meeting minutes, newsletters, photographs, and reports, as well as a specific departmental and program records relating to the Community Hospital Industrial Rehabilitation Program (CHIRP), the DeJarnette State Sanatorium, and the Shenandoah Geriatric Treatment Center (SGTC). Also included are financial records such as auditor's books, budget files, farm production records, and supply inventories. The patient-related records include admission registers, commitment papers, medical records, and several types of patient lists. Also included in this collection are a variety of report books created and maintained by staff members regarding patient admissions, attendants' rounds, ward activities, and many other duties performed at the hospital. The records of the Western State Hospital document many facets of the institution's operational history, patient life and medical treatment, as well as the evolution of mental health treatment in the Commonwealth of Virginia.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into the following series:
Series I. Administrative Records, 1825-2000
Subseries A. Annual Reports, 1836-1994
Subseries B. Board of Directors Records (and State Mental Health, Mental Retardation and Substance Abuse Services Board Records), 1825-1991
Subseries C. Buildings, Facilities and Grounds Records, 1828-1994
Subseries D. Correspondence, 1825-1944
Subseries E. DeJarnette Personal Files, 1906-1965
Subseries F. Employment and Personnel Records, 1915-1981
Subseries G. Executive Committee Records, 1841-1903
Subseries H. General Files and Ledgers, 1828-1997
Subseries I. Meeting Minutes, 1944-1991
Subseries J. Newsletters, 1940-1996
Subseries K. Photographs and Slides, circa 1880s-2000
Subseries L. Policies and Procedures, 1854-1983
Subseries M. Press Material, 1949-1998
Subseries N. Reports, 1828-1991
Subseries O. Theses and Papers, 1968-1990
Subseries P. Publications, 1905-1948
Series II. Departmental and Program Records, 1942-1983
Subseries A. Community Hospital Industrial Rehabilitation Program (CHIRP) Files, 1962-1979
Subseries B. DeJarnette Sanatorium Files, 1942-1947
Subseries C. Shenandoah Geriatric Treatment Center (SGTC) Files, 1970-1983
Series III. Financial Records, 1838-1985
Subseries A. Accounts for Board, 1838-1936
Subseries B. Auditor's Books, 1841-1930
Subseries C. Budget Records, 1927-1984
Subseries D. Expenditure and Purchasing Records, 1840-1985
Subseries E. Farm and Sewing Production Records, 1860-1945
Subseries F. General Financial Ledgers and Journals, 1884-1921
Subseries G. Indices (Miscellaneous), undated
Subseries H. Patient Account Records, 1851-1957
Subseries I. Sales Books, 1894-1936
Subseries J. Special Funds Records, 1850-1958
Subseries K. Steward's Records, 1853-1936
Subseries L. Supply Inventories, 1847-1968
Series IV. Patient Records, 1826-1996
Subseries A. Admission Records, 1828-1996
Subseries B. Application Registers, 1859-1943
Subseries C. Case Books, 1828-1910
Subseries D. Commitment Records, 1826-1900
Subseries E. Indices (Miscellaneous), 1906-1907; undated
Subseries F. Lists, 1828-1949
Subseries G. Medical Records, 1897-1980
Subseries H. Personal Effects Registers, 1855-1976
Subseries I. Postal Records, 1939-1945
Subseries J. Transportation Records, 1882-1970
Subseries K. Death and Burial Registers, 1828-2001
Series V. Report Books and Other Registers, 1847-1988
Subseries A. Admission Report Books, 1966-1975
Subseries B. Attendant's Report Books, 1868-1944
Subseries C. Day Reports, 1867-1882
Subseries D. Diet Lists, 1907-1915; undated
Subseries E. Entertainment Registers, 1939-1942
Subseries F. Guestbooks, 1967-1988
Subseries G. Library Records, 1865-1971
Subseries H. Medical Procedure and Supply Registers, 1923-1965
Subseries I. Nightly Report Registers, 1851-1944
Subseries J. Officer of the Day Books, 1939-1950
Subseries K. Out Books, 1888-1944
Subseries L. Ward Reports, 1866-1947
Subseries M. Wash Lists, 1887-1888
Subseries N. Visitor Registers, 1847-1878
Series VI. Records Found at Eastern State Hospital, 1825-1918
Subseries A. Correspondence, 1835-1918
Subseries B. Subject Files, 1825-1873
Subseries C. Volumes, 1856-1859
Series VII. DeJarnette Sanatorium Admission Registers
Contents List
- Series I. Administrative Records, 1825-2000., Extent: 77.75 cubic feet of records and 69 volumes.
  Contains a variety of records including annual and other miscellaneous reports, building and grounds records, correspondence, meeting minutes, newsletters, policies and procedures, photographs and slides, press material, subject/general files, and student papers and theses. This series serves as a "catch-all" for records without a definite office of origin, but which shed light on various aspects of the administration of Western State Hospital. Most of the records originated from or are thought to have been created and/or collected by the Superintendent (also known as the "Director") of the hospital. However, some records may have been created and collected by other departments or offices. Though the provenance may be unclear in some cases, these records document the history of the institution and its various day-to-day activities.
  - Series I., Subseries A. Annual Reports, 1836-1994.
    Contains annual reports for the Virginia Department of Mental Health and Mental Retardation, the State Hospital Board, and Western State Hospital as well as all their earlier incarnations. The latest agency, board, and instution names found in the material are used here for simplification purposes. The reports and supplements are part of accessions 31030 and 41404.
    - Department of Mental Health and Mental Retardation, 1952-1975.
      Contains annual reports of the department spanning the years 1952-1956 and 1974-1975. These reports document the year in review for the entire state agency. The reports often contain statistical and financial information for each institution under its governance, as well. This state agency has changed names several times since its inception. In the 1950s it was referred to as the Department of Mental Hygiene and Hospitals. It became the Department of Mental Health and Mental Retardation in 1973, and then the Department of Mental Health, Mental Retardation and Substance Abuse Services in 1987.
      Arranged chronologically.
      - 1952-1956. (Box 1, Folder 1)
      - 1974-1975. (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - State Hospital Board, 1942-1950.
      Contains annual reports created by the Virginia State Hospital Board. Information for each institution under the Board's governance (Central State Hospital, Eastern State Hospital, Southwestern State Hospital, Western State Hospital, Lynchburg Colony and Petersburg Colony) can be found in each booklet. The reports detail patient movement, activities, financial statistics, property values and insurance information, and personnel data. Statistical tables containing patient data can be found at the end of the report for each institution.
      - 1942-1943. (Box 244, Folder 1)
      - 1943-1944. (Box 244, Folder 2)
      - 1944-1945. (Box 244, Folder 3)
      - 1945-1946. (Box 244, Folder 4)
      - 1949-1950. (Box 244, Folder 5)
    - State Hospital Board (supplements), 1951-1958.
      Contains statistical supplements created by the State Hospital Board that were meant to accompany the annual reports of the Board. The supplements do not contain the complete annual reports, but only the tables and charts that were supposed to be included with them. Information for each institution under the Board's governance can be found in each supplement.
      - 1951. (Box 1, Folder 3)
      - 1952. (Box 1, Folder 4)
      - 1953. (Box 1, Folder 5)
      - 1954. (Box 1, Folder 6)
      - 1955. (Box 1, Folder 7)
      - 1956. (Box 1, Folder 8)
      - 1957. (Box 1, Folder 9)
      - 1958. (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Western State Hospital, 1836-1994.
      Contains the annual reports of Western State Hospital that were submitted to the General Assembly by the Court or Board of Directors every year. Researchers should note that Western State Hospital has changed names several times during its history. In its earliest years it was sometimes referred to as "Western Hospital," as well as the more commonly used, "Western Lunatic Asylum." Between 1861 and 1865, it was known as Central Lunatic Asylum (not to be confused with the hospital of the same name later built in Petersburg, Virginia). The name was eventually changed to Western State Hospital by an Act of the General Assembly in 1894. The reports were compiled by the superintendent and contain financial information, as well as patient-related statistics. These charts often note specific mental conditions, place of patient origin, and if or when an elopement, discharge or death occurred. Other topics are addressed when necessary, and include discussions of medical techniques, equipment or employment needs, patient life, and overall management of the hospital. All of the earliest reports are handwritten, and some are merely rough drafts or notes. Since this is not a comprehensive collection of annual reports, it may be necessary to look elsewhere for those that are missing. In the earliest years, annual reports for state institutions were part of the rough journals of the House of Delegates (1826-1846). Later, they became part of the Governor's message and annual reports of the public officers of the state (1847-1860s). Annual reports for all of Virginia's state agencies (1860s and beyond) were bound together as "Annual Reports of Officers, Boards and Institutions of the Commonwealth of Virginia," (call no. JK3930.A21). Additional annual reports for Western Lunatic Asylum, most notably the report from 1861, can be found in the Records of Eastern State Hospital.
      - 1836-1850. (Box 2)
      - 1888-1894. (Box 2)
      - 1835-1840. (Box 3, Folder 1)
      - 1841. (Box 3, Folder 2)
      - 1845. (Box 3, Folder 3)
      - 1848. (Box 3, Folder 4)
      - 1851-1857. (Box 3, Folder 5)
      - 1863-1869. (Box 3, Folder 6)
      - 1871-1873. (Box 3, Folder 7)
      - 1877-1878. (Box 3, Folder 8)
      - 1879-1880. (Box 3, Folder 9)
      - 1879-1881. (Box 3, Folder 10)
      - 1883-1884. (Box 3, Folder 11)
      - 1886-1887. (Box 3, Folder 12)
      - 1888. (Box 3, Folder 13)
      - 1888-1889. (Box 3, Folder 14)
      - 1889-1890. (Box 3, Folder 15)
      - 1890-1891. (Box 3, Folder 16)
      - 1892-1893. (Box 3, Folder 17)
      - 1893-1894. (Box 3, Folder 18)
      - 1895-1896. (Box 3, Folder 19)
      - 1896-1897. (Box 4, Folder 1)
      - 1897-1898. (Box 4, Folder 2)
      - 1899-1900. (Box 4, Folder 3)
      - 1903-1904. (Box 245, Folder 1)
      - 1904-1905. (Box 245, Folder 2)
      - 1905-1906. (Box 245, Folder 3)
      - 1906-1907. (Box 245, Folder 4)
      - 1907-1908. (Box 245, Folder 5)
      - 1908-1909 [also contains annual report for Virginia State Epileptic Colony at Lynchburg, 1906-1909]. (Box 245, Folder 6)
      - 1909-1910. (Box 245, Folder 7)
      - 1910-1911. (Box 245, Folder 8)
      - 1911-1912. (Box 245, Folder 9)
      - 1912-1913. (Box 245, Folder 10)
      - 1913-1914. (Box 4, Folder 4)
      - 1914-1915. (Box 245, Folder 11)
      - 1915-1916. (Box 245, Folder 12)
      - 1916-1917. (Box 246, Folder 1)
      - 1917-1918. (Box 246, Folder 2)
      - 1918-1919. (Box 246, Folder 3)
      - 1919-1921. (Box 246, Folder 4)
      - 1921-1923. (Box 246, Folder 5)
      - 1923-1925. (Box 246, Folder 6)
      - 1925-1926. (Box 246, Folder 7)
      - 1927-1928. (Box 246, Folder 8)
      - 1928-1929. (Box 246, Folder 9)
      - 1929-1930. (Box 246, Folder 10)
      - 1930-1931. (Box 246, Folder 11)
      - 1931-1932. (Box 246, Folder 12)
      - 1932-1933. (Box 246, Folder 13)
      - 1933-1934. (Box 246, Folder 14)
      - 1934-1935. (Box 246, Folder 15)
      - 1935-1936. (Box 246, Folder 16)
      - 1936-1937. (Box 246, Folder 17)
      - 1937-1938. (Box 246, Folder 18)
      - 1938-1939. (Box 4, Folder 5)
      - 1939-1940. (Box 247, Folder 1)
      - 1940-1941. (Box 247, Folder 2)
      - 1941-1942. (Box 247, Folder 3)
      - 1942-1943. (Box 247, Folder 4)
      - 1943-1944. (Box 247, Folder 5)
      - 1944-1945. (Box 247, Folder 6)
      - 1945-1946. (Box 247, Folder 7)
      - 1952-1953. (Box 4, Folder 6)
      - 1953-1954. (Box 4, Folder 7)
      - 1954-1955. (Box 4, Folder 8)
      - 1955-1956. (Box 4, Folder 9)
      - 1955-1956. (Box 4, Folder 10)
      - 1957-1958. (Box 4, Folder 11)
      - 1958-1959. (Box 4, Folder 12)
      - 1960-1961. (Box 4, Folder 13)
      - 1962-1963. (Box 4, Folder 14)
      - 1962-1963. (Box 4, Folder 15)
      - 1963-1964. (Box 4, Folder 16)
      - 1963-1964. (Box 4, Folder 17)
      - 1964-1965. (Box 5, Folder 1)
      - 1964-1965. (Box 5, Folder 2)
      - 1967-1968. (Box 5, Folder 3)
      - 1968-1969. (Box 5, Folder 4)
      - 1969-1970. (Box 5, Folder 5)
      - 1970-1971. (Box 5, Folder 6)
      - 1971-1972. (Box 5, Folder 7)
      - 1971-1972. (Box 5, Folder 8)
      - 1972-1973. (Box 5, Folder 9)
      - 1973-1974. (Box 5, Folder 10)
      - 1973-1974. (Box 5, Folder 11)
      - 1975-1976. (Box 5, Folder 12)
      - 1975-1976. (Box 5, Folder 13)
      - 1976-1977. (Box 6, Folder 1)
      - 1976-1977. (Box 6, Folder 2)
      - 1977-1978. (Box 6, Folder 3)
      - 1977-1978. (Box 6, Folder 4)
      - 1978-1979. (Box 6, Folder 5)
      - 1978-1979. (Box 6, Folder 6)
      - 1979-1980. (Box 6, Folder 7)
      - 1979-1980. (Box 6, Folder 8)
      - 1980-1982. (Box 6, Folder 9)
      - 1981-1982. (Box 6, Folder 10)
      - 1987. (Box 6, Folder 11)
      - 1988. (Box 7, Folder 1)
      - 1988. (Box 7, Folder 2)
      - 1989. (Box 7, Folder 3)
      - 1990. (Box 7, Folder 4)
      - 1990. (Box 7, Folder 5)
      - 1991. (Box 7, Folder 6)
      - 1992. (Box 7, Folder 7)
      - 1992. (Box 7, Folder 8)
      - 1993. (Box 7, Folder 9)
      - 1994. (Box 7, Folder 10)
    - Other Institutions/Hospitals, 1878-1984.
      Contains scattered annual reports created by the other Virginia State Hospitals, Colonies, and Training Centers. The reports detail patient movement, activities, financial statistics, property values and insurance information, and personnel data. In the earlier publications, statistical tables containing patient data can be found at the end of the reports.
      - Central Lunatic Asylum, 1878-1879. (Box 247, Folder 8)
      - Central State Hospital, 1903-1904. (Box 247, Folder 9)
      - Central State Hospital, 1907-1908. (Box 247, Folder 10)
      - Central State Hospital, 1908-1909. (Box 247, Folder 11)
      - Central State Hospital, 1930-1931. (Box 247, Folder 12)
      - Central State Hospital, 1943-1944. (Box 247, Folder 13)
      - Central Virginia Training Center, 1983-1984. (Box 247, Folder 14)
      - Eastern State Hospital, 1927-1928. (Box 247, Folder 15)
      - Eastern State Hospital, 1975-1976. (Box 247, Folder 16)
      - Lynchburg State Colony, 1939-1940. (Box 247, Folder 17)
      - Lynchburg State Colony, 1940-1941. (Box 247, Folder 18)
      - Lynchburg State Colony, 1944-1945. (Box 247, Folder 19)
      - Lynchburg Training School and Hospital, 1981-1982. (Box 247, Folder 20)
      - Petersburg State Colony, 1938-1939. (Box 247, Folder 21)
      - Petersburg State Colony, 1940-1941. (Box 247, Folder 22)
      - Petersburg State Colony, 1942-1943. (Box 247, Folder 23)
      - Southwestern State Hospital, 1906-1907. (Box 247, Folder 24)
      - date. (Box b, Folder f)
  - Series I., Subseries B. Board of Directors Records (and State Mental Health, Mental Retardation and Substance Abuse Services Board Records), 1825-1991.